<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2578 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2578.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1065 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1065.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1157 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1157.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1213 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1213.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3588 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3588.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5226 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5226.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5792 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5792.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5793 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5793.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2865 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2865.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5424 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5424.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5612 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5612.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6350 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6350.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5280 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5280.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5284 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5284.xml">

]>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?> <!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- OPTIONS, known as processing instructions (PIs) go here. -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of PIs,
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable PIs that most I-Ds might want to use. -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?> <!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC): -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?> <!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="2"?> <!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references: -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?> <!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?> <!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space: 
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?> <!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?> <!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of popular PIs -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-liang-iana-pen-07" ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
  	<title abbrev="IANA PEN v2.0">IANA Registration Considerations for Private Enterprise Numbers (PENs)</title>
    <author fullname="Pearl Liang" initials="P" surname="Liang">
      <organization>ICANN</organization>
      <address>
	        <postal><street>12025 Waterfront Drive, Suite 300</street>
	        <city>Los Angeles</city><region>CA</region><code>90094</code>
			<country>USA</country></postal>
<!-- <phone/> -->
<!-- <facsimile/> -->
      <email>pearl.liang@icann.org</email>
<!-- <uri/> -->
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="A." surname="Melnikov" fullname="Alexey Melnikov">
      <organization>Isode Ltd</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>5 Castle Business Village</street>
          <street>36 Station Road</street>
          <city>Hampton</city>
          <region>Middlesex</region>
          <code>TW12 2BX</code>
          <country>UK</country>
        </postal>
        <email>Alexey.Melnikov@isode.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2015"/>
<!-- <area/> -->
<!-- <keyword/> -->
<!-- <keyword/> -->
<!-- <keyword/> -->
<!-- <keyword/> -->
    <abstract>
      <t>
Private Enterprise Numbers (PENs) are a technical protocol parameter frequently used
for network management, and in protocols such as
LDAP, DIAMETER or GSS-API.  This document 
discusses what a PEN is, common uses for PENs, and
IANA's registration procedures PENs.  The registration 
procedures include instructions and requirements for obtaining a new
PEN, modifying existing registrations, and the
removal of existing registrations.
</t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">

  <t>
    A Private Enterprise Number (also known as a "PEN"), is a non-negative integer, unique within
    the iso.org.dod.internet.private.enterprise (1.3.6.1.4.1) Object Identifiers (OIDs<!--////Alexey: add reference for OIDs-->) subtree
    of the ISO Object Identifier (OID) hierarchy. This hierarchy, jointly developed by ITU-T
    and ISO/IEC was developed to name "any type of object, concept or 'thing' with a globaly unambiguous name
    which requires a persistent name" (See http://www.oid-info.com/#oid).
    The sub-tree for which the IETF is the Registration Authority, originally defined in <xref target="RFC1065"/>,
    is used to allow any entity to obtain a globally unique identifier to reference
    an organization ("enterprise") in <!--IETF-defined--> protocols.
<!--
    The iso.org.dod.internet.private.enterprise OID is known as the Private
    Enterprise Number OID.
-->
<!--From RFC 2578:
      The private(4) subtree is used to identify objects defined
      unilaterally.  The enterprises(1) subtree beneath private is used,
      among other things, to permit providers of networking subsystems to
      register models of their products.
-->
  </t>

  <t>To date, the procedures for the assignment of new PENs and
     the modification of assigned PENs have not been clearly documented.  
	   Private Enterprise Numbers are referenced in RFCs  <xref target="RFC1157"/> <xref target="RFC1213"/>
	   and <xref target="RFC2578"/>.
	   These documents primarily define Simple Network Management Protocol (SNMP), 
	   Management Information Base (MIB) and Structure of Management Information (SMI) structures.
	   As such, none of these RFCs clearly describe PENs nor do they define PEN registration procedures.
	</t>

	<t>
    As a result of the lack of documented process, updates to assigned PENs can be challenging.

    Given there are no clear registration requirements, it can be difficult to
    validate change requests, particularly in cases
    such as updates to organization names or legal ownership, changes to
    email addresses of the registered PEN owner, etc.
  </t>

	<t>
	   This document introduces PENs, how they are commonly used, and
     their registration and update procedures.
	</t>

    </section>

    <section title="Introduction to Private Enterprise Numbers">
      
	<t>
    PENs are frequently embedded in OIDs (Object Identifiers) <!--////Alexey: add reference for OIDs-->,
    which are most often used in Simple Network Management Protocol (SNMP)
    Management Information Base (MIB) configurations.
    However, PENs are not designed to be used exclusively for SNMP purposes,
    but rather they can be and are used by a variety
    protocols and Data Manipulation Languages.
    There is no restriction for using private enterprise numbers for other protocols
    or data models than SNMP or MIB.</t>

  <t>
    If the OID is only to be used privately, then enterprise numbers are to be used.
    PEN is a number under the prefix 1.3.6.1.4.1. and PEN appears as follows:
    
      <list>
        <t>
          Prefix: iso.org.dod.internet.private.enterprise.(Your node)<vspace/>
          1.3.6.1.4.1.xxxx
        </t>
      </list>
  </t>

  <t>
    IANA only manages and maintain this hierarchy tree under the IESG guidelines.
    There are many other prefixes, such as 2.16.840.1113883, 1.2.840.113549.1.9.16.2.21,
    etc., under completely different arcs and managed by other repositories (which might or
    might not be managed by IANA).
    This document doesn't cover management of these other repositories.
  </t>

<!--Alexey: not sure about this
  <t>OID-info.com has detailed resources on OIDs  See: http://oid-info.com/faq.htm#3.</t>
-->
      
	  <section anchor="others" title="Various Uses of PENs &quot;in the wild&quot;">

<t>
PENs as integers are used in many ways. In IETF protocols, they are often used in extension
mechanisms to cause an extension to have a unique identifier.
Examples of protocols that use PEN values in their extension mechanisms include
RADIUS <xref target="RFC2865"/>,
DIAMETER <xref target="RFC3588"/>,
Syslog <xref target="RFC5424"/>,
RSVP <xref target="RFC5284"/>,
and vCard <xref target="RFC6350"/>.
</t>

<t>
PENs as part of an OID are also used in protocols for extension identification, although generally only in protocols that
already use OIDs as identifiers. For examle, extensions in PKIX <xref target="RFC5280"/> are given as OIDs,
so private extensions that use PENs would use the full OID.
</t>

<t>
The places that PENs are used is completely up to implementers. Neither IANA nor the IETF police how
people use the numbers out in the wild, nor do they have any say in disputes about how any
particular PEN might or might not be used.
</t>
      
    </section>

  </section>

  <section title="PEN Assignment">

    <t>
    Assignments of PENs are done by the Internet Assigned Numbers Authority (IANA).
    This section provides information relating to the assignment of new PENs and
    the requirements associated with updating already assigned PENs.
    </t>

    <section anchor="new-assignment" title="Assignment of a New PEN">

      <t>
        PENs are assigned through a "First Come First Served" registration policy as described in <xref target="RFC5226"/>.
        They are assigned sequentially.   There is no opportunity to request a particular private enterprise number.
      </t>

      <t>
        A PEN can be requested by individuals or organizations in order to obtain a unique value for their
        "enterprise". Requests for new PENs can be submitted via an automated form at IANA.
      </t>

      <t>
        In order to facilitate appropriate registration, and in particular, subsequent update of an assigned PEN,
        a small amount of information is required. This information includes
        the name and contact information of the requesting organization (or individual),
        the name of the contact person for the PEN, and an e-mail address of the contact.
      </t>

      <t>
        <!--/////Alexey: open issue, need more text to discourage that-->
        Historically, users submit a program name, product, project, and random abbreviation as
        the organization name to when applying for a PEN.  This practice is discouraged
        since multiple programs, product, and/or projects can have their own sub-trees under the PEN assigned
        to the organization (or individual), thus there is rarely a need for an organization
        to have multiple IANA-assigned PENs.
      </t>

      <t>Before requesting additional OIDs, IANA encourages the identification of any existing
      OID assignment(s) to the requesting organization (or individual) and the creation of sub-trees
      where possible and appropriate. IANA may decline the allocation of new PENs to organizations
      that have existing registrations unless justification for multiple allocations is provided.</t>

    <t>The following information will be requested for a new registration:</t>
    
		<t> Registrant (Company/Organization) Name in ASCII (REQUIRED)</t>
		<t> UTF-8 version of the Registrant (Company/Organization) Name (OPTIONAL)</t>
		<t> Registrant (Company/Organization) E-mail Address (REQUIRED)</t>
		<t> Registrant Postal Address (REQUIRED)</t>
		<t> Contact Name (REQUIRED)</t>
		<t> Contact E-mail Address (REQUIRED)</t>
		<t> Contact Postal Address (OPTIONAL)</t>
		<t> Contact Phone Number (OPTIONAL)</t>
    <t> Reference (OPTIONAL)</t>
    <t> Comments (OPTIONAL)</t>
		<t>
			Registrant (Company/Organization) Name: The name of 
			the organization or individual responsible for the registration 
			of Private Enterprise Number.  If the organization is a company, 
			it should be the full legal name including "Inc.", "Ltd.", etc.  
		</t>

    <t>UTF-8 version: If a UTF-8 version of the company name is available, the requester
    can provide the UTF-8 name.  This will be listed in the registry.
    </t>

		<t>
		Registrant (Company/Organization) E-mail Address: An e-mail 
		address belonging to the organization that requests the PEN.  This e-mail 
		address will be publicly available in the IANA PEN Registry.  
		The E-mail address should be a valid email address and can be 
		a role account e-mail address.
	</t>
		<t>
      Registrant Postal Address: The postal address/location of
      the organization/individual requesting the PEN.
      This information is only used by IANA for verification and will be kept private.
    </t>
		<t>
      Contact Name: Name of the individual who will be
      responsible for the PEN on behalf of the company.
      This Contact person is authorized to submit changes on behalf of
      the Registrant (Company/Organization) described above.
    </t>
        
		<t>
			Contact E-Mail Address: The e-mail address of the individual 
			responsible for the PEN.  The e-mail address must be one the Contact
			person can email confirmation from.  This e-mail address will be 
			publicly available in the IANA PEN Registry.  The Contact E-mail 
			Address can be the same one as the Registrant's E-mail address. 
		</t>

		<t>
			Contact Postal Address: The full postal address of the individual 
			responsible the PEN, including state/province, zip/postal code, 
			country, etc.  
		</t>
		<t>
			Contact Phone: The telephone number (with extension where appropriate) 
			of the individual responsible for the PEN, including country code.
		</t>
    <t>
    		Reference: A document associated with the implementation of the OID 
    		can be referenced with the registration.  
    </t>
    <t>Comments: This field will contain the old Registrant/Company Name associated with a PEN if applicable.</t>
        
		<t>It is recommended that a single PEN is granted per organization.  IANA 
			does not expect to allocate additional PENs to the same Registrants 
			(Companies/Organizations) that have existing PEN records listed 
			in the IANA PEN registry.</t>
        
    </section>
      
    <section anchor="update" title="Update of an Assigned PEN">
    		
		<t>When a Company/Organization has been merged or acquired by another enterprise, 
		the Registrant (Company/Organization) Name can be annotated in the registry.
    IANA will verify the requested changes, and, if it deems to be
    necessary, official letters from the existing owner might be required.
    It is not guarantee that the request will be granted if
    IANA does not have sufficient information to verify the changes, or
    if there is legacy use of the PEN out in the wild.
    </t>

		<t>All information associated with existing PEN records, excluding the Registrant (Company/Organization) Name, 
			shall be updated if the information is obsoleted.  (See the preceding section to update the Registrant 
			(Company/Organization) Name.)  A request to update Contact information associated with an existing PEN 
			record shall be submitted via an automated form at IANA.  Requests can only be fulfilled upon 
			verification by IANA and/or subject matter experts.  Additional documentations will be required if it 
			deems to be necessary to validate the request.</t>
		
		<t>A change to the Contact Name of existing PEN records can be made to IANA in case of personnel changes, 
			change of employment, acquisitions, etc.  It would be ideal that new requests shall be completed by 
			the existing Contacts for the PEN records.  E-mail verifications of the requested changes are required.  
			Alternatively, supplemental documentations and/or letters issued by the Company/Organization (Registrant 
			Name) will be required if E-mail verifications cannot be fulfilled and if it deems to be necessary. </t>
      
    </section>

    <section anchor="Removals" title="Removals of Private Enterprise Numbers">
    			
    <t>Such request does not happen often and regularly.</t>

		<t>Considering the fact that there might be legacy uses of any existing allocation, registrations SHOULD NOT 
			be removed.</t>
			
		<t>A Contact Name can request to remove the corresponding Contact information if the company is no longer
		in operation, the Contact does not wish to be listed in the IANA PEN registry and
		if the PEN is no longer believed to be in use.  The Modification 
		procedure described above SHOULD be followed.</t>
		
		
		<t>Requests can only be fulfilled upon verification by IANA and/or 
			subject matter experts if it deems to be necessary.
		</t>

    	<t>IF the removal request is honoured, the entry is marked as "Unassigned"
<!--////Alexey: some of the entries in the registry are actually marked as "Reserved".
        Are these errors in the registry?-->      
	   and annotated as "returned on yyyy-mm-dd by xxxxxxx".
	   A future update to this document can allow IANA to reallocate such returned PEN,
	   however this document doesn't allow for that.</t>

    	</section>

    </section>

    <section title="Registration in the Private Enterprise Number registry">

      <section title="Registration of PEN" anchor="registry-content">
        
        <t>The registry table consists of a list of the following properties:</t>

        <t> PEN number</t>
        <t> Registrant (Company/Organization) Name (in ASCII)</t>
        <t> UTF-8 version of the Registrant (Company/Organization) Name</t>
        <t> Registrant (Company/Organization) E-mail Address (REQUIRED)</t>
        <t> Contact Name</t>
        <t> Contact E-mail Address</t>
        <t> Date Assigned</t>
        <t> Date Modified</t>
        <t> Reference</t>
        <t> Comments</t>

        <t>NOTE: See <xref target="new-assignment"/> for definition of these properties.</t>

        <t>o  Values marked as "Reserved" (excluding value zero) in the registry can not be reassigned
        to a new company or individual without consulting IESG (or expert(s) designated by IESG).
        Reserved entries mark entries with unclear ownership.</t>

        <t>o  Value "Unassigned" SHOULD NOT be re-assigned unless specified 
			  otherwise, i.e. when the available pool of PENs runs out.</t>
        
      </section>

      <section anchor="syntax" title="Syntax for Private Enterprise Names and PENs">

        <t>
          o  UTF-8 Names of Private Enterprises MUST satisfy the requirements of the
          NicknameFreeformClass <xref target="I-D.ietf-precis-nickname"/>.
          (<!--////Alexey: Verify the explanation-->
          Basically, this means that all ASCII letters, ASCII digits, ASCII punctuation characters,
          Unicode symbols are allowed.)
        </t>

        <t>o  Names of Private Enterprises MUST NOT begin or end with a hyphen</t>

        <t>
          o  Maximum value for PENs is hereby defined within 2**32-1 with 0 and 0xFFFFFF (in hex) marked as Reserved.
          (Note that while the original PEN definition has no upper bound, this document defines the upper bound,
          because some protocol make assumptions about how big PENs can be.
          For example, DIAMETER <xref target="RFC3588"/> assumes that this value is no bigger than 2**32-1.)
          <!--pearl: i cannot be sure if we can insert the upper limit and mark it as "Reserved" in the registry as it's an event-triggered base page. -->
        </t>

      </section>

    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      
	    <t>
		  The authors would like to thank Dan Romascanu, Michelle Cotton, 
		  and Bert Wijnen for their contributions to this document.
	    </t>
      
    	<!--///Pearl: to add Benoit? -->
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">

      <t>
      This document requests IANA to update the PEN online template forms both NEW and Modification
      as defined in sections <xref target="new-assignment"/> and <xref target="update"/>.
      </t>

      <t>
      The PEN registry should be updated to include the information as defined
      in <xref target="registry-content"/>.
      </t>

<t>
There is a PEN number, 32473, reserved for use as examples in documentation.
This reservation is described in <xref target="RFC5612"/>.
</t>

      <section anchor="Historic" title="Historical Assignments">
    		<t>This document will correct the missing historical assignments that 
    			predates ICANN's management of the existing registry.  These entries
          will be marked as "Reserved" and annotated as "Returned on yyyy-mm-dd" in the registry.
          These numbers MAY be re-assigned when the available pool of
          PENs runs out upon instructions from IESG (or IESG assigned expert(s)).</t>

          <t>2187, 2188, 3513, 4164, 4565, 4600, 4913, 4999, 5099, 5144, 5201, 5683,
    			5777, 6260, 6619, 14827, 16739, 26975</t>
          
          <t>The range from 11670 to 11769</t>
    		
    	</section>
      
    </section>
    
    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
	  <t>
        See the Security Considerations section in BCP 26 <xref target="RFC5226"/>,
        and note that improper definition and application of IANA registration policies
        can introduce both interoperability and security issues.
        It is critical that registration policies be considered carefully and separately
        for each registry.
        Overly restrictive policies can result in the lack of registration of
        code points and parameters that need to be registered, while overly permissive
        policies can result in inappropriate registrations.
        Striking the right balance is an important part of document development.
      </t>

      <t>
        As mentioned in a preceding section, given there are no clear registration requirements
        in the past, only limited information is recorded, significant out-of-date information
        is listed in the registry, and there is no strong authentication mechanism in place,
        the implications (if any) of the theft of PENs is possible.  There is a possibility
        that the registration data can be transferred to someone else unintentionally.
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
	      &RFC2119;
	      &RFC5226;

        <reference anchor="I-D.ietf-precis-nickname">
          <front>
            <title>Preparation and Comparison of Nicknames</title>
            <author initials="P" surname="Saint-Andre" fullname="Peter Saint-Andre">
              <organization/>
            </author>
            <date month="January" day="23" year="2014"/>
            <abstract>
              <t>
                This document describes how to prepare and compare Unicode strings representing nicknames, primarily for use within textual chatrooms. This profile is intended to be used by messaging and text conferencing technologies such as the Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP), the Message Session Relay Protocol (MSRP), and Centralized Conferencing (XCON).
              </t>
            </abstract>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-ietf-precis-nickname-09"/>
          <format type="TXT" target="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-precis-nickname-09.txt"/>
        </reference>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
    	  &RFC1065;
	      &RFC1157;
	      &RFC1213;
	      &RFC2578;
        &RFC3588;
	      &RFC5280;
	      &RFC5284;
	      &RFC5424;
	      &RFC2865;
	      &RFC5612;
	      &RFC5792;
	      &RFC5793;
	      &RFC6350;
    </references>

    <section title="Acknowledgements">

      <t>David Conrad edited an earlier version of this document.</t>

    </section>

<!-- Changes from last versions:

- Changes in 05:
1. cleaned up some redundant texts
2. modified the Reserved value not for allocation


- Changes in 04:
1. Use draft-ietf-precis-nickname to describe allowed Unicode characters in Names of Private Enterprises.
2. Clarified the limit of 2**32-1 on PENs.
3. Reordered requirements, so that requirements on Names of Private Enterprises and PEN values are grouped together.
4. Replaced one use of Reserved with Unassigned.

- Changes in 03:
1. Removed an internal note in the IANA Considerations section.
2. Editted the "Modification of Private Enterprise Numbers" section to 
clarify that the Registrant/Company Name can be changed with verification.
- 

-->
  </back>
</rfc>
